片名：無法無天
CITY OF GOD
幹，雞跑了，快去追那只雞
Fuck, the chicken's got away!
Go after that chicken, man!
快點，捉住那只雞
Go on, for fuck's sake!
Get that chicken!
拍得好我就能進報社
If it’s a good photo,
I'll get a job at the paper.
-是嗎？ -總得冒個險
-You think so, Rocket?
-Gotta take the risk.
為一張照片賭命？算了吧
You'd risk your life
for a picture? Forget it!
你以為我愛惹那些流氓？
You think I want to meet up
with that motherfucking hood?
老兄，捉住那只雞
Get that chicken, bro!
媽的，叫你捉住，讓開
Motherfucker! I told you
to grab that chicken!
Outta my way!
捉住那只雞
Get that chicken!
小霸王會宰了你
If Li’l Z' catches you,
he'll kill you.
他得先找到我
Yeah, well,
he's gotta find me first.
小子，捉住那只雞
捉住那只雞
Hey, kid! Get that chicken!
Get that chicken!
媽的，條子
Shit! The cops!
不准跑
Don't fucking run off!
給我
Give me that.
梅隆海，娘娘腔
Hey, Melonhead! You fucking fag!
一張照片可以改變我的人生
A picture could change
my life, but...
但在天主之城，逃走會被逮到
in the City of God, if you
run away, they get you...
留下來也會被逮到
他們正朝著我們來了
-They’re coming for us!
...and if you stay, they get you too.
從我小時候就是這樣
It's been that way
ever since I was a kid...
（60年代）
THE SIXTIES
你真沒用
You’re useless, man!
-去撿球啦 -廢物
-Go get the ball!
-Fucking useless!
小子，把球給我玩
Hey, kid!
Give me the ball, I wanna play.
-又不是你的 -你想惹我嗎？
-It’s not yours.
-You wanna mess with me?
滾開
Fuck off.
- 你叫什麼？
- 抱歉，忘了自我介紹
-What’s your name?
-Sorry, I forgot to introduce myself.
-阿炮 -阿炮，聽我的話
-My name’s Rocket.
-Some advice, Rocket...
別讓小豆子碰球，他遜斃了
Don’t let Li’l Dice
touch that ball. He sucks.
-你輸了 -走，阿毛
-You lose, pal.
-Go, Shaggy!
這是阿毛
That's Shaggy.
天主之城的故事得從他說起
To tell the story of the City of God,
I have to start with him.
8，9，10，11…
8, 9, 10, 11...
不過要講他就得提到少年三俠
But in order to tell Shaggy's story, I
must tell the story of the Tender Trio.
阿毛，瓦斯車來了，你還混？不是怕了吧？
Well, Shaggy? The gas truck’s coming.
You’re not gonna chicken out...
What are you fucking around for?
（少年三俠的故事）
THE STORY OF THE TENDER TRIO
少年三俠在天主之城很有名
The notorious Tender Trio
was legendary in the City of God.
阿毛
Shaggy...
阿夾
Clipper...
還有阿呆
and Goose.
小豆子和阿毛的弟弟班尼是跟班
Li’l Dice and Benny...
Tagging along were always
Shaggy's brother.
我沒膽跟著我哥阿呆
I never had the courage
to follow my brother, Goose.
快點
Okay, let’s go.
阿呆，快上
Let’s go!
Come on, Goose.
停車
Stop! Stop!
Stop this fucker!
停車，否則開槍
Stop or I’ll shoot, motherfucker!
下車
Get out!
快下來，把錢拿來
Hurry up, asshole!
Gimme the money!
誰要瓦斯？
Who wants gas?
你想為老闆的錢送命？
More! You wanna die for your
boss’ damn money?
這裡有好多錢
Shitloads of money here!
你活該，混蛋…
You see, asshole?
Asshole!
靠，條子
Fuck! The cops!
我們快離開這裡
快閃，到處都是條子
Let’s get outta here!
Clear out! The place is
crawling with cops!
-阿毛 -阿呆，給你
-Shaggy!
-The ball, Goose, it’s yours!
我曾以為少年三俠
Back then, I thought
the guys in the Tender Trio...
是里約熱內盧最狠的角色
were the most dangerous hoods
in Rio.
拿去買新球
Here! Buy some new balls.
其實他們只是半調子
But they were just amateurs.
我哥也一樣
這些給爸
-Even my brother, Goose.
-Rocket, give this money to dad.
別說是我給的，好嗎？
But don’t tell him it’s from me.
Okay?
-嗨，阿猛 -什麼事？
-Hey, Stringy!
-Yeah?
阿猛，我有好多錢
Look how much I’ve got.
我們來天主之城尋找天堂
We came to the City of God
hoping to find paradise.
許多家庭毀於水災…
Many families were homeless
due to flooding...
和貧民區常見的縱火案
and acts of arson
in the ghettos.
路燈，要有電了
-A light post!
-We’ll have electricity!
政府高官不是蓋的
The bigwigs in government
didn't joke around.
無家可歸？去天主之城
Homeless? Off to City of God!
這裡沒電、路沒鋪、沒公車
There was no electricity,
paved streets or transportation.
但權貴者才不管我們死活
But for the rich and powerful
our problems didn't matter.
里約熱內盧早已遺忘了我們
We were too far removed...
from the picture postcard image
of Rio de Janeiro.
你覺得我會成為救生員嗎？
Do you think I can become
a lifeguard one day?
我不知道
I don’t know.
當救生員比賣魚好
Being a lifeguard is better
than a fishmonger.
我不想賣魚，好臭
I don’t want to sell fish.
It stinks.
-你在罵你爸？ -不是
-Are you insulting your father?
-No.
那你想當什麼？
So what do you want to be?
不知道
I don’t know.
-反正不當流氓或員警 -為什麼？
-Not a hood or a policeman.
-Why not?
我怕中槍
I’m scared of getting shot.
把槍收起來
Put that thing away, kid.
Are you nuts?
拿槍指著我，你瘋啦？
Pointing that gun at me?
別這麼凶，小豆子是我弟
Take it easy with the kid, Goose.
Li’l Dice is with me.
對啊，我也是流氓
Right, I'm a gangster too.
這次沒搶到多少
-That gas truck didn't bring much.
-So what?
反正我們每天都搶，一天一台
-We rob gas trucks every day.
-One today, another tomorrow.
我們得搶有錢人
No, we need to rob
some rich guy’s house.
才能離開這裡
That’s the only
way to get outta here.
不對，你們應該聽我的
Hell, no. What you need
is to follow my plan.
That’s it.
小鬼頭很屌喔
The little fart’s getting
too big for his britches!
哈了麻就開始胡扯
He gets high and starts
talking bullshit.
你們兩個還不及他的一半
You two junkies aren't worth
half as much as that kid.
你有什麼主意？
What you got in mind, Li’l Dice?
混兄弟除了有槍，還要有點子
To be a real hood you need
more than just a gun. You need ideas.
小豆子就有
And Li’l Dice had them.
-就是這家？ -對
-Is that the motel?
-Yeah.
進去搶了錢就閃，不要殺人
We go in, grab the money and
get out. No killing, got that?
我需要槍
-I need this.
-Don’t touch my gun, kid.
-別碰我的槍 -不准再打我
Don’t ever do that again.
-別指著我 -笨蛋
-Don’t point at me.
-Fuck you.
-別用手指著我 -少幼稚了
-Don’t point your finger at me!
-Stop acting like a baby!
這把給你
Here’s yours.
-酷 -走吧
-Awesome!
-Let’s go!
-等一下 -幹嘛？
-Not so fast!
-What?
你留著把風
You stay here and keep watch.
條子來了就射那扇窗戶
If the cops come, shoot that
window over there.
-為什麼？叫那個呆子做 -聽著…
-Why me? Let that dork do that.
-Look...
我免費提供計畫
那傢伙最沒用了
I gave you this great plan, for free...
While that guy’s absolutely useless!
-你只有點子 -沒錯
-You just had the idea.
-Exactly!
You’re just a kid, remember?
你還小
你掩護我們
You cover us, okay?
遲早會輪到你，不要心急
You’ll get your turn, so cool it.
Stop trying to rush things.
留在這裡
You stay there.
（出口）
這是搶劫
This is a hold-up, bitch.
你們應該去上學或工作
You should be studying or working.
You don't even look like hoodlums.
你們甚至不像流氓
你們應該去工作…
Instead, you ought to be
working or studying, boy.
閉嘴，煩死了
Shut up!
What a pain in the ass!
好了嗎？
Okay, Clipper?
進去吧
Shall we go in?
我沒有點東西
I didn't order anything.
旅館請客，把錢交出來
It’s on the house, sir.
Hand over the money!
別怕，我只要你的現金和皮夾
Keep calm, all I want
is your cash.
-別指著我… -你的皮夾…
-Don’t point that...
-Your wallet...
老兄，這是什麼妓院？
Hey, man...
What kind of whorehouse is this?
你信教？ 對
-You from the church?
-Yes, brother.
拿錢來
Give it to me!
賤人
Slut!
你人老肉又塌
You're old, fat and flabby!
想跟她一樣嗎？
Wanna take her place?
怎麼回事？
What’s going on?
-條子，快跑 讓我們修理它 -快
-The cops! Let’s beat it!
-Let’s go!
開那輛車，我去叫小豆子
Take that car.
I'll go get Li’l Dice.
好屌的車
Jesus, what a car!
-小豆子不見了 -條子開槍了，走吧
-Something fucked up. Li’l Dice’s gone.
-The cops are shooting, let’s go!
慢一點，等一下
Slow down! Hold on...
你說你會開車
我會啊，別吵
-You said you knew how to drive.
-I do, so cool it!
轉彎，小心
Turn! Watch out!
你這個混蛋
You fucking asshole!
我又不是故意的
Hey, I didn’t do it on purpose.
你們什麼都沒看到
不准多嘴
No one saw anything.
So keep your mouths shut, understand?
等等，我扭到了
Hold on, I twisted my ankle.
阿夾扭到了
Goose fucked up his ankle.
好痛
It fucking hurts.
帶他進樹林，我開槍引開員警
Take him into the woods.
I’ll shoot to distract the cops.
-我們信靠神 -我們信靠神
-In God we trust.
把電話給我
Pass me the telephone, Penguin.
矮子在天主之城也很有名
Shorty is another notorious guy
in the City of God.
待會再來聊他
But it's not yet time
to tell his story.
阿呆，我好痛
閉嘴
-It fucking hurts, Goose.
-Shut up.
等一下，你好娘娘腔
-Wait up...
-You sound like a damn sissy, man.
-把手給我 爬上來
-沒有人看到？
-Give me your hand! Climb up!
-No one saw anything?
怪了，一輛車沖進酒吧
卻沒有人看到
How odd! A car crashes
into a bar and no one saw a thing.
你也沒看到吧？
I suppose you didn’t see
anything either?
還是一樣一問三不知
As usual, no one saw,
no one knows.
矮子，你好嗎？
So what’s up, Shorty?
他們躲在林子裡
They’re hiding in the woods.
-梅隆海 -你打算怎麼做？
-Hello, Melonhead.
-How are you doing?
我覺得他們在樹林裡
I have this feeling that
they’re out in the woods.
-應該錯不了 -該死
-The motherfuckers.
-They’re out in the woods.
菲利浦，鎖車，藍傑，跟我來
Felipe, lock up the car.
Rangel, come with me.
這麼暗，他們怎麼看得到
I can’t see a thing.
How the hell can they see?
爛樹林
Fucking jungle.
-他們搶了不少 -我知道
-They stole a fortune at that motel.
-I know.
我們把錢吞了吧
What if we took the money?
你瘋了嗎？我不想汙錢
Are you crazy?
I’m not getting mixed up in that.
我要剷除他們
I want to exterminate these guys.
偷黑人和賊的錢又不犯法
What? Since when is stealing from
niggers and thieves a crime?
要捉他們並不難，我有眼線
It won't be hard to nab them.
I have a stoolie in the City.
-你聽到槍聲了嗎？
-被我逮到就死定了
-Did you hear those shots?
-If I catch one of them, I'll kill him.
瑪拉卡娜
Maracana!
快開門
Open the door.
-怎麼了？-條子在追我
-What’s the matter?
-The cops are after me.
阿毛…阿毛
Shaggy!
條子就在後面，借我躲
-Shaggy!
-The cops are on my ass!
快進來
-Hide me!
-Quick, come in.
媽的
就知道會耗上整晚
Shit... I thought the cops
would be down there all night.
我看到一個景象
I had a vision, Goose.
你有哈麻嗎？
You been smoking something?
-你工作過對吧？ -對
-You've had a job, right?
-Yeah.
別人怎麼說？
What’s it like?
What do people say?
我是在幫我爸
I worked with my father.
當爸爸的屁話最多了
And fathers talk a lot of shit.
你知道嗎？
我不幹了
You know what, Goose?
I'm getting out, I don't want to die.
-我不適合混兄弟 -等等，條子還沒走
-This gangster’s life isn’t for me.
-Wait! The cops are still down there.
我不在乎
I don’t give a shit.
我要回教會
I'm going back to the church.
住在至高者隱密處的
He that dwells in the secret
place of the most High...
必住在全能者的蔭下
shall abide under the shadow of
the Almighty. I will say of the Lord...
我要論到耶和華說
He is my refuge and my fortress,
in Him will I trust.
他是我的避難所，是我的山寨 是我所倚靠的
Fear not the terror by night,
nor the arrow that flies by day...
你必不怕黑夜的驚駭 或是白日飛的箭
也不怕黑夜行的瘟疫 或是午間…
nor the pestilence that walks
in darkness, nor the destruction...
-站住，不准動 -站住
-Stop, motherfucker!
-Don’t move!
否則開槍
Stop, or I’ll shoot!
必住在全能者的蔭下…
...shall abide under the shadow
of the Almighty.
這是城裡最血腥的一起搶案
The hold-up at the motel went down
as the bloodiest in history.
三俠的命運就此分歧
The destinies of the outlaws
then took different paths.
我覺得他不是搶匪
I don’t think this guy
was involved in the heist.
你看
See here?
-他是工人，不是流氓
-我現在說他是
-He’s a worker, not a hoodlum.
-I’ll make him one now.
命運讓阿夾重回上帝懷抱
Destiny put Clipper
back into the hands of God.
讓阿毛愛上貝妮絲
Shaggy was in Bernice's hands.
讓阿呆回來找我爸
And Goose was
in my father's hands.
為什麼做壞事？當我是白癡？
Why do you do these things?
You think I’m a fool?
以後跟著我賣魚
From now on,
you’ll work with me.
你弟會幫忙盯著你
Your younger brother
will keep an eye on you.
你給我聽好
You listen to me.
你再去搶錢，我就宰了你
If I catch you with money that
isn't yours, I'll kill you.
你也一樣
你也一樣，快換衣服上工
That goes for you too. Get changed!
You start work immediately.
哥哥是流氓
遭殃的總是你
Having a hood as a brother sucks.
You always end up footing the bill.
放心，爸氣完就沒事了
Don’t worry.
Dad’s mad at me...
but he’ll get over it.
拿來，這不是你該碰的
你要念書
Give me that, Rocket. It’s not
for you. You have to study.
-你不怕挨槍嗎？-我腦筋不好
-Getting shot doesn’t scare you?
-I’m a hood because I got no brain.
你很聰明，應該念書
But you’re smart.
You should study.
我上學是因為討厭勞動
I go to school because
I don’t like physical work.
答應我絕不碰這把槍，好嗎？
Promise me something... That you’ll
never touch this gun. Promise?
握手為定
Let’s shake.
動作快
We’d better hurry.
我要賣很多魚，不要笑
I’m gonna sell a lot of fish.
And don’t laugh.
我挨打時你還偷笑
You grinned when I got slapped.
-我？ -我看見了
-Who, me?
-I saw you.
怎麼？舌頭打結了？
What is it, Shaggy?
Cat got your tongue?
你這樣晃我會緊張
Your fidgeting behind me
makes me nervous.
-我在想該說什麼 -你也會思考？
-I'm thinking of what to say to you.
-You’re thinking, as well?
小心出事
Don’t. It’ll be your downfall.
我為你傾心，我很重感覺
My heart has chosen you.
And I follow my heart.
你在耍我嗎？
Are you pulling my leg?
你沒聽過一見鍾情嗎？
You never heard of
love at first sight?
-兄弟沒有情，只有欲望
-你老是打斷我的話
-Hoods don’t love, they desire.
-You cut down everything I say.
兄弟不說話，只說花言巧語
Hoods don’t talk,
they smooth-talk.
那我就不浪費口水了
Well, I’ll stop wasting
my breath on you.
兄弟從不罷手，只會先暫停
Hoods don't stop,
they take a break.
跟你求愛真複雜
Talking to you about love
sure is complicated.
這不是愛，是騙局
It’s not love,
it’s a con game.
可是我愛你
It’s just that I love you.
你或許會說服我
You just might end up
convincing me...
案發後，員警經常跑來搜查
After the hold-up, there were
constant police raids in the ghetto.
每天都有人入獄
有人被捕
Every day, someone went to jail,
someone was nailed.
但每個人都一問三不知
But no one had seen anything.
No one knew anything.
沒有人向警方透露搶匪的去處
No one blabbed to the cops about
where the thieves were hiding out.
（3個月後）
3 MONTHS LATER
阿毛，你怎麼不改變一下？
Why don’t you change your life?
Shaggy...
去找份工作，別整天賴床
Get a job instead of
lying around in bed all day.
-一無是處 -什麼意思？
-Good-for-nothing!
-What do you mean?
你工作就能賺錢？
You think you can make money
working? Go ahead.
沒錯，你以為我在忙什麼？
That’s right, Shaggy...
what do you think I do all day?
別激動
我只想跟你生孩子，買塊地
Take it easy, baby... you know all
I want is to be with you, have kids...
養養雞，種大麻來抽
and a farm, raise chickens,
grow pot and get high.
是啊，都是花言巧語
Sure! For me, that’s
nothing but smooth-talk.
我搶那次差點就發了
What? I almost got
rich with that motel job.
有沒有搞錯
Are you kidding?
條子還在為那裡的命案找你
The cops are still looking for you
because of the deaths in the motel.
什麼命案？你說什麼？
What deaths?
What are you talking about?
你是目擊者嗎？不懂就閉嘴
Did you see anything?
You don’t know shit, so shut up.
你又不在，我沒有殺人
You weren’t there.
I didn’t kill anyone.
一定是員警殺人，找我頂罪
I bet it’s those fucking policemen,
and I’m the one taking the rap.
他們還捉了小豆子 別再提了
They even nabbed Li’l Dice.
So don't bring it up again!
-我不管是誰幹的 -不是我
-I don't care who did it.
-It wasn’t me.
我這麼說吧，我不要跟流氓生孩子
Let me just say... I don’t want my
kid’s father to be a hoodlum.
你沒人理了
You’re all alone, Shaggy.
-沒人理？ -沒錯
-All alone?
-That’s right!
-阿夾去信教 -哈利路亞
-Clipper’s gone religious.
-Hallelujah!
-阿呆在工作 -馬屁精
-Goose is working.
-Ass-kisser!
-你呢？ -我沒變，那又怎樣？
-And you?
-I haven’t changed. So what?
是他們背棄我
They’ve deserted me,
that’s all.
那我也要這麼做
Then I’m deserting you too.
我要離開這裡，你想來就來
I’m splitting, Shaggy.
Come with me, if you want.
否則我自己走
Otherwise, I’ll go alone.
魚貨大特價
Fish for sale!
我哥答應不再鬼混
My brother had promised
to stop messing around.
但兄弟從不罷手
只會先暫停
But a hood doesn't stop,
a hood takes a break.
阿呆搞上了矮子的老婆
Goose began messing around
with Shorty's wife.
我特地為你這種貴客
I have trout. But for special
customers like you...
準備了接吻魚
I also have a kisser fish.
那是鯡魚
Hey, that’s a mullet!
你老公會替你口交嗎？
Doesn’t your husband...
go down on you?
不會
No.
我老公都會先幫我口交半小時
Mine, before entering me,
has to use his tongue.
你有讓他肛交嗎？
For about half an hour.
And from behind? Do you let him?
當然沒有，不會痛嗎？
前幾次會
-Good God, no. Doesn’t it hurt?
-The first few times.
之後可爽了，不過得準備香蕉
Then you’ll see, it’s fantastic.
But you need a banana.
幹什麼？
What for?
你真不懂得享樂
You’re missing the good things
in life, girl!
你把香蕉準備好
You take a banana, warm it up...
後面上了，前面就塞香蕉
Put it up your thing, while he
takes you from behind.
爽死了
去問你老公
It’s a real rush!
Ask your husband.
不行，你不瞭解他，他八成會揍我
I couldn’t. You don’t know him.
He’s liable to beat me.
試試看，男人最愛這種花招
Try him. Men go wild
for smut like that.
死黑鬼
Motherfucking nigger!
蕩婦
Slut!
賤人
Whoring bitch!
阿炮，把短褲給我，快
Rocket, give me your shorts.
Quick!
-快脫下來
-我才不要光屁股
-Take them off, dammit!
-I'm not going naked in the street.
你想看我死嗎？
快把短褲給我
You want your brother to die?
Give me your shorts. Now!
你的衣服給我
Give me your shirt.
你的短褲，快點
Your shorts! Hurry up!
每次我都得替他擦屁股
I knew it. It’s always me
who forks up for that bum.
那個混蛋跑了，那是他弟弟
The bastard ran off.
That's his brother.
-那個小鬼？ -我要閹了那傢伙
-That brat there?
-I’ll castrate that fucker.
魚貨大特價
Fish! Fish for sale!
小朋友，過來
Hey, kid, come over here.
-你哥呢？ -他今天沒上工
-Where’s your brother?
-He’s not working today.
-上車 -我又沒做壞事
-Oh yeah? Get in.
-I didn’t do anything.
-上車 -那魚呢？
-Get in!
-What about my fish?
快點
-Hurry it up, kid!
-I don’t want to lose my fish!
-我不想把魚扔著 -別管魚了
-給我那個 -坐下
-Forget your fish.
-Sit your ass down.
-無所謂
-我爸會殺了我
-My father will kill me.
-That doesn’t matter.
走吧，什麼都沒有
Let’s go.
There’s nothing here.
那天，爸發誓再也不想見我哥
That day, my father swore he never
wanted to see my brother again.
走吧
Let’s go, Felipe.
確實沒有人再見到他
And he never did. No one ever
saw him in the ghetto again.
少年三俠的故事即將結束
The story of the Tender Trio
was coming to an end.
小豆子？媽的，我以為你掛了
Li’l Dice? Shit, man. I thought you
were a goner at the motel.
-你好有錢
-別給他，那是我們的
-You’re fucking loaded!
-Don’t, Benny. That’s our money.
去你的，少廢話，錢拿來
Fuck you. Cut the crap
and give me the money.
班尼，告訴阿毛矮子告密了
Benny... Tell your brother Shaggy
that Shorty is squealing.
我要離開這裡
但矮子忙得很
-I'm leaving the ghetto.
-But Shorty had his hands full...
阿猛，快
Let’s go see, Stringy.
天亮前有鄰居報警
A neighbor called the police
before sunrise.
小報也跑來了
The tabloids went to town:
※狠心丈夫活埋妻子§
"Man Buries Wife Alive
in the City of God"
除了記者，還來了一堆條子
Along with reporters, the place
was swarming with cops.
流氓都閃光了
The hoodlums took off.
-你找死啊？ -是你找死
-You wanna die?
-It’s you who’s gonna die...
if you don’t do what I say.
照我的話去做 對她客氣一點
And show the lady more respect.
快開車
Let’s go, dammit!
-前面有條子 -管他的，開車
-There are cops ahead.
-Fuck them, let’s go.
-去哪裡？ -隨便，快走
-Where to?
-Anywhere, just go.
-怎麼搞的？
-我的天哪
-What’s the matter?
-Have mercy!
饒了我吧，這輛車很破
-This car’s a piece of junk.
-My ass! Start the damn thing!
-少來，快發動 -得下去推車
It needs a push.
快去
Push, Shaggy!
去啊
Push!
是你？
You?
你想捉賊？在那邊
You want to arrest the thieves?
Over there...
捉住那個人
Nab that guy over there!
阿毛，快點
Run, Shaggy!
停車
Stop the car!
-這邊，他在那裡
-抓住那傢伙
-This way! He’s over here.
-We got that sonofabitch!
-笨蛋 -他是兇手
-He’s a murderer.
-The bastard!
阿毛死的那天，有人群圍觀
On the day Shaggy died
I remember the crowds...
還有人照相
and a camera.
我一直想要一台相機
I’d always wanted to have one.
去上學吧
Let’s go to school.
-如何？ -去海邊吧
-Well?
-Let’s go to the beach.
但是要考試
But we have an exam.
那又怎樣？
So what?
其他人都去了
Everyone else is at the beach.
走吧
Come on, let’s go!
她穿比基尼還不去
She’s in a bikini,
but doesn’t want to go.
你到底有什麼？
What’s that saying you have?
海邊不是人人都能去的
The sun is for everyone. The beach,
for those who deserve it.
（70年代）
THE SEVENTIES
看這邊
我16歲買了第一台相機
-Over here!
-I bought my first camera...
我很窮，所以從等級最低
when I was 16. Like all poor people,
I started at the bottom...
最便宜的機種買起
with the world's cheapest model.
阿炮，怎麼樣？
So, Rocket?
How are things going?
開葷了沒？
Any luck getting laid yet?
還沒
Zilch.
安潔莉卡，我為她瘋狂
你還在拍？
-Angelica. I was crazy about her.
-So, Rocket, still clicking away?
她很漂亮，而且有經驗
She was gorgeous and the only
girl in our gang who screwed.
我想跟她做第一次
I wanted to lose
my virginity with her.
跟她？她有男朋友
With her, buddy?
She’s got a guy.
-我又沒吃醋
-她爸是軍人
-So? I’m not jealous.
-Her father’s a sergeant.
人都有缺點
往中間靠
No one’s perfect.
Closer together!
我是這票朋友裡的攝影師
I was the official
photographer of our gang.
我們自稱爵士人
大家都會付錢跟我買照片
The gang of groovies. Everyone
paid to have copies of the pictures.
提亞哥，往後一點
Thiago, move back a little.
這樣行嗎？
很好
-Is this okay?
-Perfect.
我想抽大麻
I need a joint.
別抽了，現在流行吸白粉
Instead of smoking, man,
you should snort coke. It’s far out.
你有在吸？我比較喜歡哈麻
You snort, Thiago?
I prefer a good toke.
我可以幫你弄到貨
If you like,
I can get it for you.
是嗎？那就快去
You can? Then go on,
move your ass!
但白粉才優，是真正的醉麻劑
But the choice stuff is coke.
That’s a real nercotic.
是麻醉劑
Narcotic!
你的嘴好鹹
去你的
-Your mouth is all salty, Thiago.
-Screw you.
阿猛，你想當救生員？
You want to be
a lifeguard, Stringy?
-你從不下水 -你說什麼？
-You’re never in the water.
-My dad’s a lifeguard.
-賭一罐啤酒我比你行
-賭了
-I’ll bet you a beer I swim better.
-You’re on.
我可以去找黑仔弄一根
If you like, I can go get you
a joint at Blacky’s.
我願意為她做任何事
I’d have done anything
to please her...
替她買大麻、白粉
Buy her pot, coke...
我可以去找角頭
用低價買到好貨
I could go to the top dogs to buy
quality stuff at a good price...
因為角頭黑仔是我的老同學
because the local boss
was a former classmate: Blacky.
誰？
阿炮
-Who is it?
-Rocket.
-最近好嗎？ -很好
-How are things down there?
-Fine.
-其他人呢？ -也很好
-And the kids?
-Fine too.
-你想買還是抽？
-買
-You want to buy or smoke a joint?
-Buy.
進來
Come in, buddy.
誰？是誰？
Who is it?
這是黑仔的地盤
This was Blacky's turf.
但原本也不是他的
But it hadn't always been his.
-黑仔 -靠，小豆子
-Hey, Blacky.
-Fuck, Li’l Dice.
來我這裡還帶人
誰說這裡是你的？
-You show up like this at my place?
-Who said it was your place?
（這間公寓的故事） 杜菲賽麗守寡之後開始販毒
THE STORY OF THE APARTMENT
Dona Zelia began selling drugs here...
好養活她的女兒
when her husband died,
in order to raise her daughters.
她會送毒品給為她服務的男孩
She also gave away drugs to boys at
times in return for special favors.
她最喜歡大個兒
後來大個兒長大了
Her favorite was "Big Boy".
One day, he grew very big!
賽麗太外行，三兩下就被取代
Zelia's operation was so amateur that
he had no trouble seizing it from her.
大個兒利用青少年販毒
Big Boy used the neighborhood
kids as dealers.
那我的份呢？
去吃屎吧
-What about my pot?
-Stick it up your ass.
最會做生意的…
The best dealer...
是紅毛
...was Carrot.
-我可以喝一口嗎？ -當然
-Can I have a sip?
-Sure.
他贏得信任，被升為經理
He earned Big Boy's trust...
was promoted, and moved up to
become a manager.
黑仔，我們20你5
Blacky, 20 for us and
5 for you, okay?
有一天紅毛的朋友跑來
One day a buddy of Carrot's
showed up.
他叫亞裡斯多德
我老婆要開刀
-His name was Aristotle.
-My wife needs an operation.
他們家在紅毛落魄時收留他
His family had taken Carrot in
when he was down and out.
兄弟有難，他不能不幫
He couldn't refuse to help
a brother in need.
這是貨，週五之前交錢
Here’s the dope. I want
the dough no later than Friday.
-你救了我一命 -星期五
-You’ve bailed me out, brother.
-Friday.
他就像我的親兄弟
He’s my buddy, practically
my brother, Big Boy.
再給他一星期
Give him another week.
你不殺他，我就殺你
紅毛別無選擇
-Either you kill him, or I'll kill you.
-Carrot had no choice.
-別這樣，別開槍
-我說星期五
-I said Friday.
-Don’t do it, man.
紅毛想殺了大個兒，不過不必
Carrot wanted to kill Big Boy,
but it wasn't necessary.
大個兒沒收買條子，死在獄中
Big Boy hadn't paid off the cops.
He died in jail.
紅毛接收了大個兒的一切
Carrot took everything
that belonged to Big Boy...
但房子他不要
but didn’t want the apartment...
他把它送給親信珨黑仔
the place was ill-fated. Carrot gave it
to his most trusted dealer...
給你，150袋
-Here. 150 bags.
-Blacky.
多給一點，這裡很競爭
Give me more. This place
is crawling with druggies.
於是他接收了這個地盤
That's how he took over
the local trade.
但為時並不久
But not for long...
誰？是誰？
Who is it?
去看看
Go see.
-黑仔 -靠，小豆子
-Hey, Blacky.
-Fuck, Li’l Dice.
來我這裡還帶人
誰說這裡是你的？
-You show up like this at my place?
-Who said it was your place?
是啊，誰說的？
Yeah, who?
小豆子，怎麼了？
-Something wrong, Li’l Dice?
-Li’l Dice, my ass.
什麼小豆子，我現在叫小霸王
My name is Li’l Z’ now.
（小霸王的故事）
THE STORY OF LI’L Z’
小霸王從還叫小豆子的時候
Li’l Z' had always wanted
to be boss of the City of God...
就想當天主之城的龍頭
ever since he was little
and was called "Li’l Dice".
不讓我過癮？
They’re having fun,
and not me?
我想趕快走
I want to get out of here.
幹什麼？你朋友搶過了
你還想怎樣？
What, kid? Your friend took
everything. What do you want?
那一晚，小豆子如願殺了人
That night, Li'l Dice
satisfied his thirst to kill...
他知道阿毛不會放過他
though he knew Shaggy would
never forgive him.
他離開天主之城躲避懲罰
To avoid being punished
he left the City of God.
辛苦工作賺錢
He had to work hard for peanuts.
-小豆子和班尼混得不錯
-幹得好
-Yeah, Benny!
-Li’l Dice and Benny managed well.
他們有犯罪天份
They had the gift of crime.
-你拿得比我多 -我是主謀
-You have more money than me.
-It was my idea.
他們只怕遇見大流氓
The only problem was running into
an older hoodlum...
像我哥阿呆
小豆子？
...like my brother, Goose.
-Li’l Dice?
媽的，我以為你掛了
Shit, man. I thought
you were a goner at the motel.
你好有錢
You’re fucking loaded!
別給他，那是我們的
Don’t, Benny. That’s our money.
去你的，少廢話
Benny, tell your brother Shaggy...
班尼，告訴阿毛矮子告密了
我要離開這裡
I’m leaving the ghetto.
that Shorty is squealing.
阿呆
Goose!
這是阿毛的，帶著吧
From Shaggy. You'll need it.
小豆子在殺人的日子裡長大
From one hit to the next,
Li’l Dice grew up.
18歲就成了最受敬畏的兄弟
At 18, he was the most
respected hood in the City of God.
你成年了，小心
You’re of age now, watch out!
和里約熱內盧頭號通緝犯之一
He was one of the most
wanted robbers in Rio.
小豆子，你好嗎？
Li’l Dice, how’s it going?
生日快樂，恭喜你成年
Happy birthday.
I’m so glad you’ve turned 18...
滾開啦
抱歉
-Get lost, Tuba!
-Excuse me, amigo...
我要啤酒
Give me a beer!
混蛋，你沒看到我嗎？
Didn’t you see me, prick?
-你沒看到我嗎？ -怎麼啦？
-Sorry, man.
-Up yours!
去你的 下次一定宰了你，娘娘腔
The next time,
I’ll waste you, asshole!
Fag!
小豆子野心勃勃
Li'l Dice was ready for anything.
我有話要說
I wanna talk.
他急欲大展身手
那幾隻羊最肥？
-And he was itching to start.
-Who are the fattest cats here?
一大堆
你看傑瑞
-There are tons of them.
-Look at Jerry Adriani...
金鏈子，漂亮衣服
gold chain, snazzy clothes.
你看佩拉和他的妞
Look at Pereira
and the chick he’s with...
貝妮絲，她跟過我哥
你看他的車
-Bernice. She was my brother’s girl.
-Check out his car.
還有黑仔，金光閃閃
Then there’s Blacky.
Covered in gold.
金項鍊，金手錶
Gold chain, gold watch...
你看紅毛和他的車
Look at Carrot, and his car.
-他們都是毒販
-他們都很有錢
-They’re all dealers.
-They’re all fucking loaded.
搶劫錢太少
Hold-ups bring in chickenshit.
-毒品才有賺頭 -我懂了
-The big bucks are in drugs.
-I see.
尤其是賣白粉
Especially in selling coke.
-要有本錢 -不必
-But you need money.
-Not really...
直接殺了他們接手
We’ll kill these clowns
and take over their business.
-什麼時候開始？ -馬上
-When do we start?
-Now.
惡魔指點明路
Exu-the-Devil is the light
that shines forth.
把你帶來
He brought you here.
為何留在天主遺忘的天主之城
Why remain in the City of God
where God has forgotten you?
我知道你要什麼
你要權柄
I know what you want.
You want power.
我有東西可以讓你如願
I have something which will
give it to you.
我把護身符送給你改運
To change your fate,
I give you my protector, boy.
但你不能褻瀆它
But you mustn't fornicate
with the amulet...
否則你會死
you’ll die.
otherwise...
你不再是小豆子，而是小霸王
Li’l Dice...
but Li’l Z’.
The boy is no longer called
小霸王會長大
Li’l Z’ will grow up.
你追隨我，我就挺你
You stick with me,
I’ll stick with you.
小豆子改名小霸王，大開殺戒
Li’l Dice became Li'l Z'
and he began to kill.
他找一天拿傑瑞開刀
他整天都在幹這種事
He started one morning,
taking over Jerry Adriani's racket.
到了晚上 他幾乎併吞了全城的生意
By that night, almost all
of the rackets in the ghetto were his.
紅毛是班尼的朋友，逃過一劫
The only business he didn't
touch was Carrot's...
剩下這層公寓，不過好辦
since he was a friend of Benny's.
All that was left was the apartment...
But that would be easy.
誰？是誰？
Who is it?
-黑仔 -靠，小豆子
-Hey, Blacky.
-Fuck, Li’l Dice.
來我這裡還帶人
誰說這裡是你的？
-You show up like this at my place?
-Who said it was your place?
小豆子，怎麼了？
-Something wrong, Li’l Dice?
-Li’l Dice, my ass.
-什麼小豆子，我現在叫小霸王
-他叫小霸王
-My name is Li’l Z’ now.
-His name’s Li’l Z’, see?
-你完蛋了 -別殺他，他懂
-You’re a goner, bastard.
-Don’t kill him. He understands.
對吧？
Right, Blacky?
什麼都給你 我不想惹麻煩
It’s all yours, I don’t want anything.
I don’t want no trouble, okay?
我應該趁機替我哥報仇
I should have taken this chance
to avenge my brother's death.
饒你一命替我們工作 懂嗎？
You’ll live, but you’ll
work for us. Understand?
但說得容易
That's easy to say...
-你要去哪裡？ -不關他的事
-Where are you going?
-He’s clean, Li’l Z’.
你叫什麼？
What’s your name, kid?
-阿炮 -他是阿呆的弟弟
-Rocket.
-He’s Goose’s brother.
-阿呆？ -死掉的阿呆
-Goose?
-The late Goose.
你走吧
Quick, kid. Run along.
告訴大家現在由我當家
Tell everyone that this business
now belongs to Li’l Z’.
我們會賣白粉，懂嗎？
And that we'll be selling coke.
Got that?
古柯鹼
Cocaine.
-堂口在哪裡？ -往前左邊
-Where’s the turf?
-Over there, on the left.
販毒就像其他生意
Selling drugs is like any
other business.
供應商提供貨品，在裝配線上
The supplier
delivers the merchandise...
which is then
packaged on the premises.
進行包裝
It's done in an assembly line.
說來枯燥，大麻卷成一卷
Boring as hell...
Pot is wrapped up in "lids".
古柯鹼則裝成小包
Cocaine is put into packets...
十包或百包為一袋
and then into bundles
of 10 or 100.
販毒甚至可以當事業
You can even make a career
in dealing drugs.
先當小弟
The kids start out
as delivery boys.
拿錢負責跑腿，或是傳話
They're paid to run errands
and take messages.
然後升格把風
Then they become lookouts.
If the police arrive...
員警一來，就收風箏大家閃人
the kites disappear
and everyone scrams.
之後變成毒販或※幽靈§
Later, you become a dealer
or a "vapor".
員警一來，幽靈就會消失
When the heat's on, the
"vapor" quickly evaporates.
再往上有打手
Moving up the ladder,
you have the "soldier".
算術好的可以當經理
And if the guy is good at math,
he can become a manager...
是老大的左右手
the boss' right-hand man.
員警拿了甜頭，不會找碴
The police receive their part
and don’t make trouble.
小霸王殺光了對頭
Since Li’l Z' killed off
all of his enemies...
天主之城不再有槍戰
可以安心開車
there were no shoot-outs in the
City of God. You could drive there...
大家覺得在這裡交易很安全
The playboys felt safe
buying their drugs there.
毒蟲湧入，小霸王大發利市
The City teemed with addicts
and Li’l Z' grew rich.
-這樣夠嗎？ -成交
-Is it okay?
-It’s a deal.
-我不知道該戴哪一支
-這支很酷
-I can’t decide which to wear.
-This one’s cool.
若販毒合法，小霸王早就紅了
If dealing were legal, Li’l Z'
would have been man of the year.
但我就危險了，我很怕他
But things were risky for me.
I was afraid of him.
卻處處碰到他
煩死了
-And he was everywhere.
-What a drag this guy is.
每次想哈麻，我就得去找紅毛
Whenever I wanted to smoke a joint
I had to go see Carrot.
半卷
謝了
Half a lid. Thanks.
但是值得，我只跟安潔莉卡抽
But it was worth it.
I only smoked with Angelica.
她剛分手，我展開行動
She and Thiago had split up,
so I made my move.
我就快追到她了
照得真好
-I was about to win her over...
-These pictures are really great.
是嗎？
我這張很好看
-You think so?
-I look good here.
-你怎樣都漂亮 -我是說真的
-You look beautiful everywhere.
-I’m serious.
我也是
Me too.
夕陽、無人的沙灘
長吻
A setting sun,
a deserted beach... a long kiss...
我心想終於要來了
I was sure this was it...
結果來的是小鬼頭
But the Runts arrived.
可以給我一根嗎？
Can I have a toke?
拿去
Here.
我要走了，再見
I’m going. See you later.
安潔莉卡
Hold on, Angelica.
-你的大麻 -給你
-Your joint, man.
-Keep it.
好酷的人
What a cool guy.
那是我與小鬼頭首次接觸
That was my first run
in with the Runts.
班尼，牛排和薯條
太好了
-Steak and fries, Benny.
-Great! Here...
來
你的小費
真的？謝謝
-A tip for you.
-Really? Thanks.
-你要吃嗎？ -不要
-Wanna eat something?
-No.
可以拿表換嗎？
失去安潔莉卡後
-Wanna trade this watch?
-After Angelica left him...
提亞哥越陷越深
Thiago began snorting
more and more.
-你爺爺的？ -我爸的
-Is it your grandfather’s?
-No, my dad’s.
人一上癮就會受毒販控制
When a guy is really hooked
he ends up in the hands of the dealer.
-十包的兩袋 -一袋
-Two bags of ten.
-One of ten.
好
但是提亞哥不同
-Okay, one bag.
-For Thiago, it was different.
小心
抱歉，教父
-Watch out!
-Sorry, godfather.
我有幫你孩子施洗嗎？
Godfather, my ass.
Did I baptize your kids?
很抱歉
快滾
-I’m sorry.
-Now beat it.
黑仔，腳踏車借我
Blacky, lend me your bike.
要比賽嗎？
Hey, wanna race?
到哪裡？
高速公路
-Where to?
-Up to the highway.
-好了嗎？ -開始
-Okay.
-Ready? Go!
-很難吧？
-是啊，你好強
-Pretty tough, wasn’t it?
-Yeah, you’re good.
球鞋在哪裡買的？
Where’d you buy those sneakers?
-不是這裡 -衣服也不是？
-Not far from here.
-The shirt, as well?
-去住宅區買的 -酷
-No, uptown.
-Cool.
是名牌
It’s a designer shirt.
你可以幫我買嗎？
If I give you money
can you buy me one?
買短褲和衣服？
Shorts and a shirt?
都買
Buy whatever you can.
-你穿幾號？ -來量吧
-What size are you?
-Measure me.
-用什麼量？ -手啊
-With what, man?
-Shit, with your hand.
鞋子呢？
轉過去
Shoe size? Turn around.
班尼
你找到房子了？
-Hey, Benny!
-You got the digs?
-褲子只有一條？ -還有
-Just one pair of pants?
-No, there’s more.
-喜歡嗎？ -喜歡
-You like it?
-Yeah.
錢還有剩
There’s some change.
留著吧
酷
-Keep it.
-Cool.
這是班尼
This is Benny.
-這是阿炮 -我知道
-This is Rocket.
-Hi. I know him.
我很時髦吧
I’ve become a playboy.
兄弟們，聽我說
Hey, gangsters, listen to this...
小心一點
Watch out...
爵士迷拉屎前會搖屁股
Groovies shake their asses
before laying a big one.
是嗎？
Oh, yeah?
Fuck off, you bastards!
給我滾
敢笑我？
Making fun of me?
混蛋
Asshole!
我不是叫你殺紅毛？他在危害貧民區
Benny, didn’t I tell you to shoot Carrot?
He’s endangering the ghetto.
-別激動，去找他談 -我要宰了他
-Cool it. Go talk to him.
-I’m gonna kill that fucker.
-我要殺了他
-別老是想殺人
-Stop trying to wipe out everyone.
-I’m gonna kill him.
放心，這裡的人都很好
Don’t worry, Angelica.
The guys in here are cool.
我又不擔心
Sure, I’m not worried.
你要跳舞？那紅毛呢？
You gonna dance, Benny?
What about Carrot?
你去找他談嘛
Go on, buddy. Go talk to the guy.
班尼是天主之城最好的流氓
Benny was the coolest hood
in the City of God.
送大麻，請喝酒
He gave away pot,
paid for drinks.
小霸王則相反
Li’l Z' was the opposite.
He had one obsession:
他一心只想當老大
to be the boss of the ghetto.
他想設法接收紅毛的生意
He wanted an excuse to take over
Carrot's racket.
-紅毛 -怎樣？
-Hey, Carrot.
-What’s up?
你不該放任小鬼頭搶劫
You shouldn’t let the Runts
do hold-ups in the ghetto.
大家管好各自的地盤，好嗎？
You look after your section,
I’ll look after mine.
我要去喝酒
Got that? I'm gonna get a drink.
-阿炮，你好嗎？ -很好
-Hey, Rocket! How’s it going?
-Great.
-班尼 -你好嗎？
-Hey, Benny!
-How’s it going?
-你好嗎？ -還不錯
-Hey, Thiago. How are you?
-Good.
-可以嗎？ -當然
-May I?
-Sure...
要跳舞嗎？
Wanna dance?
去你家行嗎？
沒問題
-Is it okay at your place?
-No problem.
我爸媽出去了，你們孤男寡女
My parents are out.
You’ll be all alone with her.
你可以開炮了
小聲一點
-You can lose your virginity tonight.
-Not so loud, man!
別人會聽見
Everyone will hear.
-你好漂亮 -謝謝
-You’re beautiful.
-Thank you.
-沒事啦
-媽的
-Shit!
-Nothing’s happening.
我知道小鬼頭跟你有關係
你當我是白癡？
Look, man, I know the Runts
are associated with you.
你想搶生意？
Think I'm a sucker, you little brat?
You want to take my racket?
我想說清楚，因為你是廢物
I want to talk to you
because you’re fucking useless.
不要碰我
Get your hand away!
小鬼頭在破壞秩序
The Runts are screwing up
our security, man.
快幫他餵奶
Give the baby his bottle.
叫那些孩子住手
Carrot, just ask the kids
to cool it, okay?
紅毛沒用，任憑小鬼頭搶劫
Carrot’s useless. He lets the Runts
do hold-ups in his section.
員警來會影響生意
The police come around and
that’s bad for business.
我就看
你的面子
I’ll do it only because
I like you.
你快去幫寶寶換尿布
But you need to change
that baby's diapers.
I’ll show you who’s the baby...
你才是寶寶
叫他們別在這裡搶劫強暴
Tell the kids that in my ghetto
no one robs or rapes!
難怪你是※小§霸王
No wonder you’re "Little" Z’!
小鬼頭是一群無法無天的小孩
The Runts were kids who didn't
respect the laws of the ghetto.
他們搶住家，搶麵包店
They would mug residents,
hold up bakeries...
在紅毛那裡特別囂張
especially in Carrot's section.
你們幹什麼？
What are you doing?
老是來搶我
-You rob me all the time!
-But they didn't know...
他們不知道現在這裡有老大了
that the City had a boss now.
（謝謝惠顧）
THANK YOU FOR CHOOSING US
天主之城對居民來說變安全了
The City had become
much safer for residents.
現在幾乎沒有搶劫
There were hardly
any hold-ups now.
有事就找小霸王
You just had to go see Li’l Z'.
-走吧 -別傷害那些小鬼
-Let’s go.
-Don’t hurt the Runts.
我不會碰他們
I won’t touch them.
-牛排 -小霸王
-Hi, Steak.
-How’s it going, Li’l Z’?
-要不要去走走？ -跟你去？
-Wanna take a walk, Steak?
-With you? Hold on...
媽，我跟朋友出去
Mom, I’m going out with
my friends.
真好吃的雞
That’s the best chicken
I ever ate.
那個老頭嚇死了
你替他難過？
-The old guy was scared shitless.
-Feeling sorry for him?
怎麼可能
You’re crazy, man!
乾脆去搶銀行或超市
Why not stick up
a bank or a supermarket?
-太遜了，毒品才好賺
-沒錯，販毒
-Peanuts. Drugs are where it’s at.
-Yeah, selling drugs.
但得從小弟做起
你要嗎？
But you have to start out as a delivery
boy. You wanna be a delivery boy?
真剝削，熬好久才能爬上去
It’s a rip off.
It takes a long time to move up.
老鳥死了才能往上爬
You have to wait till an older guy
gets killed to move up.
我不想等
我要學小霸王，把他們幹掉
croaks. I'm gonna do what Li’l Z' did.
I don't wanna wait till some guy
I'm gonna wipe them all out.
在講我嗎？老大我來了
Talking about me, kid?
The boss is here.
小鬼，回來
Come back, you brat!
-動作真快
-真會跑
-They’re quick, those kids.
-They run fast.
別的都跑了 還有嗎？
They’re all gone except you.
Any others?
你們得替他們付出代價
You’re gonna pay
for the ones that escaped.
自己選，要射手還是腳？
You choose. Shall I shoot you
in the hand or foot?
快選
Come on, choose!
手還是腳？
Hand or foot?
趕快選，快選啊
Choose, for fuck's sake!
-手 -你選小手？
-Hand.
-The little hand, eh?
酷斃了
Cool.
牛排，來看看你的能耐
Hey, Steak’n’fries,
let’s see what you’re made of.
殺了其中一個
Choose and then kill
one of them.
-滾開，讓他來
-算了，讓我來
-Leave it. I’ll do it.
-Butt out, Tuba. This is for him.
快點
Go on, Steak.
選一個，然後開槍
Go on, choose one and shoot.
快點，我沒時間等你
Come on, I haven’t got all day.
快啊
看你要殺哪一個
Kill one of them.
快，我的時間有限
Let’s go, Steak.
I’m in a hurry.
我想看你有沒有種
I wanna see what you’re made of.
殺了其中一個
快點，我趕時間
很好，你辦到了
Well done!
You did it.
-你也是兄弟了
-很好，牛排
-You’re one of us. Give me five.
-Very good, Steak.
起來，回你的老鼠洞去
不准跛腳
Get up, brat. Go back
to your rat hole. Without limping!
叫其他人不准在我的地方搶劫
Tell your buddies that no one
robs in Li’l Z”s ghetto.
快去，不准跛腳
Go now.
And no limping, okay?
Cool, Li’l Z'.
小霸王贏得居民的尊敬
While Li’l Z' was winning
the respect of the residents...
班尼則贏得安潔莉卡的心
Benny was winning
Angelica's heart.
而我，仍是個窮光蛋處男
As for me, I was still
a virgin, single and broke.
我別無選擇
I had no choice.
（一個俗辣的人生）
SUCKER’S LIFE
我必須去超市上班
I had to take a job
in a supermarket.
工時長，薪水少
我巴不得被解雇
I worked long hours for chicken feed.
I wanted to be laid off...
好用遣散費買一台相機
so I could buy a camera
with the severance pay.
但我想得太美了
But things didn't
work out that way.
-是海邊那個人 -老兄
-It’s the guy on the beach.
-Hey, bro!
-還在抽好貨？ -是啊
-Still smoking good stuff?
-Yeah.
這傢伙太酷了
That guy’s too cool.
小朋友，衣服拉起來
Hey, kid. Come here.
Lift up your shirt.
這些貧民窟小孩，給臉不要臉
We give these ghetto kids a chance
and they don't appreciate it.
-那遣散費呢？ -什麼遣散費？
-What about my severance pay?
-What severance pay?
經理以為我跟他們是一夥的
That fucking manager thought
I was part of the gang.
你因嚴重失職被解雇 馬上給我滾
You’re fired for serious misconduct.
Get out. Immediately!
我一分錢也沒拿到
I didn’t get a single cent.
這仿佛一道神諭
It was like a message from God:
※蠢材，誠實沒有好下場§
"Honesty doesn't pay, sucker’."
（意圖犯罪）
FLIRTING WITH CRIME
我等了好久
上班都遲到了
The bus sure took a long time to come.
I should already be at work.
把槍藏好，你瘋啦？
Shit, hide that gun.
Are you nuts?
這是阿呆的，反正壞了
It was Goose’s.
It’s broken anyway.
是這個路線的班次少
It’s not our fault, the company
runs few buses on this line.
誰都沒有錯，都是別人的錯
It’s never anyone’s fault.
It’s always someone else’s.
苦的是勞工，還要被壓榨
But it’s the workers who suffer.
And then, they make us squeeze!
祝您晚安
Have a nice evening, ma'am.
我認識他，他也住天主之城
I know that guy.
會認出我們
He lives in the City.
He’ll recognize us.
他才不會在乎老闆的錢被搶
So? He couldn’t care less
if we take his boss’ money.
好，走吧
Okay. Let’s go.
你們不是住天主之城？
Well, boys? Aren’t you from
the City of God?
是啊
Yeah.
我讓你們一個人免費
I’ll let one of you through
without paying.
你們要念書，才能離開貧民區
You should study
so you can get out of the ghetto.
那裡條子和流氓太多了
It's too full of cops and
hoodlums.
你念過書嗎？
我上過學，當過兵
-Did you study?
-I was in school and in the army.
是營上的第一神射
I was the best marksman
in my barracks.
我只找得到這份工作
This job was all
I could find afterwards.
但我在練空手道，有別的工作
But I do karate.
If I’m hired somewhere...
我就離開貧民窟
I’ll leave the ghetto.
-我愛好愛與和平
-你打不打架？
-Do you fight, then?
-I’m for peace and love.
但必要時…
But if I have to...
會有那麼一天的
He didn't know he would have to.
不過還沒輪到帥奈德的故事
But not yet, it's not time
to tell Knockout Ned's story.
-我們該走了 -走吧
-We should be going.
-Let’s go.
-再見 -謝了
-Good bye.
-Thanks.
拜拜
See you.
我下不了手，他人很好
I couldn’t do it.
He was such a cool guy.
是啊，他是葛森的哥哥
Yeah, totally.
That’s Gerson’s brother.
回家吧
Let’s go home.
這裡只有那家麵包店
There’s nothing here
except that bakery over there.
-不知道，※搶劫§吧
-要說什麼？
-What will you say?
-I don’t know. "This is a hold-up."
這是我的電話
Here’s my number.
-你喜歡靈魂還是爵士派對？ -靈魂派對
-You like soul or groovy parties?
-Soul.
這個也沒成功
That one didn't work either.
女店員好妖嬌，還跟我調情
The counter girl was just too foxy.
And she flirted with me.
你會打給我嗎？
Will you call me?
我沒辦法對她掏槍，她好甜
I couldn’t pull a gun on her,
she was too sweet.
我同意
Yeah, I agree.
請問一下
我迷路了，巴哈怎麼走？
Excuse me. I’m lost.
How do I get to Barra?
-巴哈？ -是啊
-To Barra?
-Yes.
我心想，算這個聖保羅人衰
I thought: "Tough luck
for this guy from Sao Paulo."
-這麼巧
-我們正要過去
-In fact, we were going there.
-You’re kidding.
-你救了我一命 -沒錯
-You’re a lifesaver.
-That’s right.
因為聖保羅人都很爛
Because no guy from Sao Paulo
could ever be cool.
屍體在這邊
-The body’s over here.
-We found it, Chief.
警長，找到了
法醫先生
The forensic expert!
長得不怎麼樣嘛
-Not a pretty sight, eh?
-You said it.
-好棒的歌手 -你喜歡他？
-What a great singer.
-You like him?
我喜歡音樂，你呢？
你也喜歡大麻嗎？
-I love music. What about you?
-Tell me, do you also like pot?
我不能說沒抽過
I can’t say I’ve never tried it.
你自己找吧
The devil recognizes his own.
有紙嗎？
-Do you have papers?
-I think so.
我用完了
我這裡有
I have some.
我很會卷大麻
I’d always been an ace
at rolling a joint.
要是泡妞也這麼行
If I’d had the same skill
with girls...
就不會錯失這麼多上床機會了
I’d never have lost so many chances
to lose my virginity.
-以聖保羅人來說你很酷
-謝了
-For a Sao Paulo guy you’re very cool.
-Thanks, bro.
兇器是什麼？
What did they use?
木棒或石頭
孩子呢？
A club or a rock.
And the child?
-毫髮無傷 -謝天謝地
-Untouched.
-Thank goodness.
死了多久？
大約4小時
-How long ago?
-About four hours.
-可以搬走了嗎？ -搬吧
-Can we take it away?
-Go ahead.
兇手一定是天主之城的人
The murderer has to be
from the City of God.
混蛋，媽的
You bastard!
You motherfucker!
你一定要在這裡殺人嗎？
Did you have to kill
your chick in the ghetto?
引來一大堆條子
-The place is crawling with cops now!
-Come on, Li’l Z'.
別這樣
去你的
我得維護名譽
-Come on? Fuck you!
-I had to avenge my honor.
她家人去告我了，你很安全
Her family’s turned me in.
You won’t have any problems.
你把員警引來，你死定了
The cops are everywhere because
of you. You’re dead meat, asshole.
算了，你也打夠了
Let up, Li’l Z’.
You’ve punished him enough.
你知道規矩
You know the law.
在我的地方殺人就得死
Anyone who kills in my ghetto
has to die as an example.
那是他的事
That was his business, Li’l Z’.
聽著，離開貧民區
Listen, you sonofabitch,
get outta the ghetto.
你太不懂規矩了
You showed no respect, understand?
班尼，你太好心了，養虎為患
You know what, Benny?
You’re too nice. If you raise
a snake, expect to get bitten.
他只是個廢物
He wasn’t worth shit.
背叛者
閉嘴
-A dirty traitor.
-Shut up, Tuba.
我要帶馬子去散步
I’m going for a walk
with my girl.
好，小心
等事情平息
Okay, be careful.
When things calm down...
就繼續處理紅毛的事
we’ll get back to our business
with Carrot, okay?
你需要交個女朋友
You need a girlfriend, Li’l Z’.
你猜我在想什麼？
Know what I’m thinking, Benny?
我太性感了？
That I’m so sexy?
也有，不過還有一件事
That too. But I mean,
you know what we could do?
-我是說真的
-你還想要
-Make love again.
-I’m serious.
我們可以離開，我討厭暴力
We could go away from here.
This violence sucks.
去哪裡？
Go where?
找個農場
To a farm.
我們其實很嬉皮，不是嗎？
We’re really hippies at heart,
aren’t we?
農場？
A farm?
愛與和平？
Peace and love?
（班尼的歡送會）
BENNY’S FAREWELL
班尼人太好，不該繼續混兄弟
Benny was just too cool
to go on being a hoodlum.
他把所有的人都找來了
He succeeded in getting everybody
together for his good-bye party.
道上兄弟
The gangs...
靈魂樂迷
The soul crowd...
-總有一天，我會上教堂
謝謝你前來參加我的派對
-教徒
-The religious crowd...
-One day, I’ll go to church.
森巴樂迷
The samba crowd...
爵士樂迷
The groovy crowd...
還有沒跳過舞的小霸王
And Li’l Z', who had never
danced in his life.
-要不要跟我跳舞？ -什麼？
要不要跟我跳舞？
Want to dance with me?
-我聽不見 -要跳舞嗎？
-I didn’t hear...
-Want to dance?
不了，我有男伴
No, thank you, I’m with someone.
阿炮
Hey, Rocket!
過來，我有話要說
Come, I want to talk
to you, buddy.
你不能跟那個女的走
為什麼？
-You can’t just split with that chick.
-Why not?
我要去住農場，哈麻聽搖滾樂
I'm gonna go live on a farm,
smoke pot, listen to rock.
你要為了那個賤人拋棄一切？
You wanna throw away everything
we've accomplished for that bitch?
她不是賤人，是我的女人
She's not a bitch, she's my girl.
我們把紅毛的生意搶來給你
We’ll take over Carrot’s business,
it’ll be yours.
-別碰他，他是好人
-他是個混蛋
-Leave Carrot alone, he’s a good guy.
-He’s a motherfucker!
你看誰都不順眼，所以我要走
See? Everyone’s a motherfucker
to you. That’s why I’m leaving.
我是你的朋友，但我要退出
我非走不可
I’m your friend,
but I’m getting out.
You got to understand,
I have to go.
我愛你，但我受夠了
I love you, man,
but I’ve had enough.
混蛋，來看看你有沒有種
Motherfucker, let’s see
if you have any balls.
幹什麼？
你想死嗎？滾開
-What is this?
-You wanna die? Fuck off, bitch!
脫光，我要看你的屁股
Strip, nigger.
I wanna see your ass.
快點脫
Hurry up!
Take it all off! Now!
快脫，我要看你的屁股
I wanna see your ass.
Come on, faggot!
快啊，快點
Let’s go, nigger!
把屁股露出來
Show your ass to everyone!
別這樣
Please...
你這個失敗者
脫光，快點
-Strip, dammit!
-Hurry it up!
班尼，跟你換一袋白粉
What’s up, Benny?
This camera for a bag of coke?
-我不賣了
-給個面子，我們是朋友
-I don’t deal anymore.
-C’mon, do it for me. You’re my friend.
-這是贓物？ -是我爸的
-Is it stolen?
-It’s okay, it’s my dad’s.
你爸的？
Your dad’s?
-去找小霸王換
-阿炮會很喜歡
-Give it to Li’l Z’.
-Rocket would love this camera.
-拿去吧 -太好了
-Yeah, here.
-Great.
我來了
Here I am!
-你想當攝影師？ -對
-You wanna be a photographer?
-Yeah.
-送你一個禮物
-媽的，太棒了
-Here’s a present.
-Shit, dude! This is great!
搖屁股，快點
搖啊
Now move your ass.
Shake it!
你會照出好照片
You’ll take some great pictures.
拿來
Give me that.
-把相機還我 -不要
-Give me back the camera!
-No!
你有什麼毛病？
What’s your problem?
Are you crazy?
班尼被殺了
They’ve killed Benny!
幹，叫救護車
兇手在哪裡？
Fuck! Call an ambulance!
Where’s the motherfucker who did it?
-小霸王，班尼死了
-不，快找醫生
-Z’, Benny is dead.
-No! Call a doctor!
滾，都是你害的
Get out of here, bitch!
It’s your fault!
混蛋
Motherfucker!
紅毛呢？
Where's Carrot?
黑仔來了
Blacky's here.
他闖禍了
He's in trouble.
我完了
I’m fucked.
-為什麼？ -我完了
-I’m fucked.
-Why?
你也是
我殺了班尼，小霸王要來了
And you are too.
I think I killed Benny.
Li’l Z’ is coming
to take your place.
我們可以去舞廳幹掉他
We can get him,
he's in the dance hall.
你殺了班尼？
You killed Benny?
是他動了，我想殺小霸王
I didn’t mean to. He moved.
I was aiming at Li’l Z’.
我們快去
Come on, let’s go.
黑仔
Blacky...
你殺了天主之城最酷的流氓
You killed the coolest
hood in the City of God.
我們去幹掉小…
Let’s go get Li’l Z’.
紅毛知道現在只能靠奇跡了
Carrot knew that without Benny only
a miracle could save his business.
我們完了
We’re fucked, man.
有哪裡比天主之城
更適合發生奇跡？
But what better place for a miracle to
happen than in the City of God?
是我的甜心美眉
Look who’s here.
My sugar babe.
-讓我過去 -親一個嘛
-Let me by.
-Gimme a kiss, girl.
讓我過去，你照過鏡子嗎？
Let me by, please.
Have you seen what you look like?
小霸王，走吧
Come on, Li’l Z’.
親愛的
你好嗎？
Hi, honey.
Everything okay, baby?
問題很簡單
小霸王很醜，帥奈德很帥
The problem was simple. Li’l Z' was
ugly. Knockout Ned was handsome.
帥奈德泡妞很輕鬆
小霸王只能買或是來硬的
Li’l Z' had to pay or use force.
Knockout Ned could get any girl.
這是帥好人和醜壞人的對決
It was a duel between
the handsome good guy...
and the ugly bad guy.
-放開我
-好好享受
-Let me go!
-Just enjoy it.
反抗也沒用，你是我的了
There’s no use fighting.
You’re mine now.
豬頭，你馬子真辣
Hey, faggot, your broad’s
really hot!
我根本不敢看她
I can’t even look her in
the face now.
我沒辦法
他怎麼不殺了我？
Why didn’t that fucker kill me?
慢著
我怎麼不殺了他？
Hold on...
Why didn't I kill that fucker?
我們回去
Let’s go back.
-那紅毛呢？ -待會再說
-We’ll get back to him.
-What about Carrot?
你要殺了他？
You gonna kill him?
帥奈德，你的妞好賤
Knockout Ned, your chick’s a slut.
Come out, motherfucker!
出來
別理他
-Come out, you loser!
-Take it easy...
我要出去，放開我
I’m going out. Let me go.
葛森，回來
Gerson! Come back, son!
與你無關，我們要找你哥
This doesn’t concern you, kid.
We’re here for your brother.
有話好說，我哥脾氣很好
Let’s talk, we can work it out.
My brother’s a peaceful guy.
他不屑見我？叫他出來
Is he too good-looking
to come talk to me? Call him.
他什麼都沒做
He hasn't done anything.
你知道我是誰？
You know who I am?
-我是小霸王 -他是小霸王
-Li’l Z’, man.
-He’s Li’l Z’.
叫那個混蛋出來
Call that motherfucker!
快去
Go on, man.
別激動，我去叫他
Calm down, I’ll call him.
我的手臂受傷了，先放過紅毛
My arm! I hurt my arm.
Carrot will have to wait.
這傢伙活該
That loser got what he deserved.
走吧
Let’s go!
葛森
Gerson...
那混蛋殺了我弟
That bastard killed my brother.
我不能放過他
I can’t let that go.
-要槍嗎？
-兒子
-Want a gun?
-My son...
媽，別激動
Calm down, mom.
別這樣，媽
Please, mom...
好好擦乾淨
Do it right, asshole.
-只能這樣擦
-我怎麼會被他刺傷？
-There’s no other way.
-How’d I let that loser hit me?
Shit, that’s some hole.
-我們好像兄弟 -閉嘴
-It’s as if we were brothers.
-Shut up.
我們都傷到手臂 你是這一手，我是另一手
Both of us hurt in the arm.
You by one brother, me the other.
-閉嘴 -真難令人相信
閉嘴
It would be really funny
if we were brothers.
那個帥奈德真不賴
突然冒出來
That Knockout Ned's not bad, eh?
He came out of nowhere.
閉嘴，煩死了
Shut up, Tuba!
You're a fucking pain!
天主之城突然出現一個英雄
It was as if the City of God
had suddenly found a hero.
上帝保佑你
God bless you, son.
這孩子是自尋死路
That kid was just asking
to be killed.
幹得好
你做得很好
Well done.
You did a good job.
你最好躲起來
You’d better go hide.
我以為帥奈德會發動革命
I thought Knockout Ned
would start a revolution here.
但天主有別的計畫
But God had other plans.
牛排，那些賣家呢？
Steak,
where are all the dealers?
躲起來了，小霸王心情很差
They’re hiding.
Li’l Z’ is in a bad mood.
害人上癮之後就躲起來
They get us hooked and then
they go off and hide.
幫個忙，弄些糖粉給我
Do me a favor. Go get some
nose candy for me.
我試試看
I’ll try.
就說是提亞哥要提神
Tell them it’s for Thiago,
to keep my buzz going.
牛排，去告訴紅毛
Steak’n’fries,
go to Carrot’s and tell him...
你殺了奈德，他就放過你
Li’l Z' says that if you kill
Knockout, he’ll leave you alone.
帥奈德，你聽到了嗎？
Hey, Knockout Ned.
Did you hear that?
捉住他
Grab the kid!
你聽到了嗎？
你不跟著我們就死定了
You heard the boy? If you don't
stick with us, you're dead.
你應該跟我們一起合作
I think you should join us.
We'll be partners.
我不碰毒品
Drugs aren't my thing.
這是我跟他的私事
This is just something
between me and him.
Those guys aren’t worth shit.
他們都是垃圾
為了權力什麼都幹
They'll do anything for power.
就像那孩子
Like that kid.
他們沒血沒淚，就像這小子
They're all robots,
like this punk here.
你在想什麼？
What’s in your head, kid?
這樣是自毀前程
Can't you see you're
wrecking your life...
跟那些瘋子暴力狂鬼混
with that maniac and a bunch
of trigger-happy fools?
-你瘋了嗎？你只是個孩子
-孩子？我哈草嗑藥，殺人放火
-Are you crazy? You’re just a kid.
-A kid? I smoke, snort...
我是男人
I’ve killed and robbed.
I’m a man.
你懂個屁
Shit, you have no idea!
他很忠心，你應該加入我們
He’s attached to his gang.
You should join up with us.
要殺他嗎？
你要變絞肉了
-Shall we kill him?
-Steak, we're going to grind you.
好，我接受
太好了
-Okay, I accept.
-Great!
回去說該帥奈德和紅毛當家了
Tell your boss that Knockout Ned
and Carrot are now in command.
有一個條件，不准濫殺無辜
But on one condition:
no killing of innocent people.
我無法接受亂殺人
I can't accept that, understand?
不殺無辜
Okay, no innocent people.
牛排搞砸了
Steak fucked up!
有我的槍嗎？
-Have you a gun for me?
-No...
沒有，不過可以去搶
but we can hold up
a gun store.
小事一樁
That’s no problem.
我不想搶劫 我不是兄弟
I don’t want to hold up anything.
I’m not a hoodlum.
這是我和他的私事
This is a personal affair
between me and him, okay?
我不是兄弟
I’m not a hoodlum.
他奸了你的妞
He raped your chick...
殺了你的叔叔弟弟，轟爛你家
killed your uncle and brother,
gunned your house...
而你只殺了他一個手下
and you killed one of his guys.
你不是兄弟就出去
If you’re not a hood,
then get out.
（帥奈德的故事）
THE STORY OF KNOCKOUT NED
搶劫
This is a hold-up!
第一次…
左輪呢？
-The first time...
-Where are the revolvers?
帥奈德救了一個店員
...Knockout Ned saved a salesclerk
from being shot by Carrot.
說好不殺人的
We said no killing!
這是規則
That’s the rule.
我們來搶老闆的錢
你們希望我們走？我們也是
We want the boss’ money. Everyone
keep calm. Open the cash register!
You want us to go?
We do too.
所以動作快
So hurry up!
看地上
第二次，紅毛救了帥奈德
-Look at the ground!
-The second time...
Carrot saved
Knockout Ned's life.
奈德學到每個規則都有例外
Ned learned that there's
an exception to every rule.
這是例外
Exception to the rule.
-你是經理？ -對
-Are you the manager?
-Yes.
這是搶劫
統統趴在地上
This is a hold-up.
Everyone on the ground!
趴下
On the ground!
把錢給我
Give me the money!
我不是在說笑，誰動就讓他死
I’m not kidding.
第三次，例外成了規則
The first person who moves
is dead!
The third time, the exception
becomes the rule.
利用搶來的錢 他們準備跟小霸王拼了
prepared to face Li’l Z'.
Carrot and Knockout Ned
紅毛可以保住生意
Carrot could protect his
business.
營上第一神射的帥奈德 則想報仇
Knockout Ned...
the best marksman in his battalion,
wanted revenge.
先是義大利槍，9釐米的
First, the Italians.
This is a 9 mm.
-我看看 -不錯吧？
-Let me see.
-Not bad, eh?
-準星有問題
-我算你特價
-The sight isn’t well-aligned.
-I’ll give you a good price.
12釐米※打炮槍§…懂了吧？
The 12 mm, the "hand job".
See why?
9釐米烏茲衝鋒槍，以色列貨
An Uzi, 9 mm. It’s Israeli.
大衛之星
猶太貨
-The star of David.
-Jewish.
我要30-06步槍
I want a 30-06.
可以大幹一場了
Now we can start having fun.
要開戰了，先來禱告
The war’s on.
Let’s start with a prayer.
我們在天上的父
願人都遵你的名為聖
Our Father who art in heaven
hallowed be our name...
願我們的旨意行在地上
Our will be done...
如同行在天上
On earth as it is in heaven...
流氓有槍，但不會用
Hoodlums have guns,
but can't shoot.
帥奈德開一槍能抵小霸王十槍
was worth ten from Li’l Z”s gang.
One bullet from Knockout Ned
小霸王氣不過，展開反擊
Li’l Z' couldn't take it.
He counter-attacked.
貧民區從人間煉獄落入地獄
The ghetto had been a purgatory,
now it was hell.
我決心離開，所以去當記者
I decided to get out.
That's how I became a reporter.
好棒的照片，一定是羅葛瑞的
I bet it’s by Rogerio Reis.
Great photo!
我就說吧
What did I tell you?
我跟其他行家一樣從基層做起
Like any pro...
I started at the bottom,
way down at the bottom.
未來仍是一片茫然
Without knowing what awaited me.
我不回家，跑去報社
I’d go over to the paper.
Instead of going home
研究室有個來自天主之城的人
A guy from the City of God
worked in the lab.
你看
Check this out.
他讓我更接近生命中的最愛
He helped me move closer to
what I loved most in life.
-羅葛瑞 -你好嗎？
-Hi, Rogerio.
-How are you, Pierre?
這是阿炮，他是攝影師
This is Rocket.
He’s a photographer.
阿炮，你好
Hello, Rocket.
-他很喜歡你 -真的？
-He’s a fan of yours.
-Really?
你真有品味
You have good taste, Rocket!
-我先走了 -再見
-Well, I’m done. I’m off.
-See you.
他人真好
What a cool guy!
單純的復仇演變成大火拼
What should have been
a swift revenge...
turned into an all-out war.
天主之城一分為二
The City of God was divided.
兩區不能相通
You couldn't go from one
section to the other.
連拜訪親戚都不行
Not even to visit a relative.
員警把貧民區的人都當流氓
The cops considered anyone
living in the ghetto a hoodlum.
大家過著越戰的生活
People got used to living
in Vietnam.
越來越多人自願送死
And more and more volunteers
kept signing up to die.
他要找你
有什麼事？
This kid...
我被紅毛的小弟揍
-What do you want?
-A boy from Carrot’s gang punched me.
火拼成了藉口
The war was
an excuse for everything.
小霸王的打手踹我
One of Li’l Z”s soldiers
kicked me.
拿這把點22
Take this .22.
紅毛的人強暴我姊
The jerk who raped my sister is
with Carrot.
小霸王趕走我家
Li’l Z’ evicted my family.
我想殺人，讓別人怕我
Kill... Be respected.
我是提亞哥，班尼的朋友
-你認識字嗎？會加減嗎？
-I’m Thiago, a friend of Benny’s.
-Can you read? Can you add?
-我蠻會管生意的
-那就開工吧
-I’m pretty good in business.
-Okay, get to work.
-幹掉殺父仇人-你想幹嘛？
-你叫什麼？-奧圖
-To get my father’s murderer.
-What’s your name?
-My name’s Otto.
-What do you want?
怎麼回事？
What’s the matter?
-他是個工人 -他想要槍
-He’s a worker.
-But he wants a gun.
他撐不了1星期
He won’t last a week.
1年後，沒有人記得前因後果
A year later, no one
remembered how it had all begun.
去死吧
Take that!
兩邊都想搶對方的生意
For both sides, the aim was to take
over the enemy's business in order...
好買更多槍，搶更多生意
to buy more guns and take over
more businesses.
我哈草嗑藥，殺人放火
I’ve killed and robbed.
I smoke, snort,
我是男人
I’m a man.
媒體開始報導，警方只好干涉
The media started taking an interest.
The police had to intervene.
一名天主之城的角頭被捕
A gang leader, from the City of God,
was arrested today.
人稱帥奈德的曼紐馬恰多
Manuel Machado,
a.k.a. Knockout Ned...
遭小霸王的人槍傷送醫
was hospitalized after being
wounded by Li’l Z”s gang.
本台記者專訪到他
Our reporter interviewed him.
火拼還在持續嗎？
還在持續
-Is the war still going on?
-It's still going on.
死了多少人？
很多，大多是無辜者
-Have many people died?
-Many have died.
Mostly innocent people.
光是認識我就會被小霸王殺
Just knowing me is enough...
to get you killed by Li’l Z'.
-警方都不管嗎？
-他們捉我，不捉他
-The police don’t go in there?
-They go after me, not him.
I’ve been in jail, while he goes
我坐牢，他拼命殺人
on killing undisturbed.
員警卻不捉
And they don’t arrest him.
帥奈德說火拼將持續
Knockout Ned says
the war will continue.
蓋德警長保證將逮捕雙方人馬
Police Chief Guedes has promised
to arrest both of the gangs.
媽的
Motherfucker!
老大是我，上報的卻是他
I’m the boss here, but he gets
his picture in the paper!
-有我的照片嗎？ -只有帥奈德的
-Have you found mine?
-Just Knockout Ned’s.
繼續找，至少名字要見報
Keep looking.
At least my name’s
got to be in there.
-什麼都沒有 -你認識字嗎？
-There’s nothing.
-Can you read?
只認得照片
Just the pictures.
什麼都沒有
Nothing.
喂，你幹什麼？
Hey, what the fuck are you doing?
那是分類廣告
我不管，要全都看過
-It’s just the want ads.
-I don’t care, read everything!
-上面又沒有新聞
-你想挨子彈嗎？
-But there aren’t any articles.
-Want a bullet in your head?
讓他們知道誰是老大
Gotta show them who’s boss here.
-把相機給我 -不要
-Give me the camera!
-No way!
幫我照相
Take my picture, man.
我按不下去
I can’t work it.
快點
Go ahead.
-我來穩住法冠
-我試試看
-I’ll hold the Beretta.
-Let me try...
讓開
Back off...
-按不下去
-真是一群飯桶
-There’s no click.
-What a bunch of bozos!
帶著你們穩死的
I’m fucked with you guys.
我知道了
I have an idea.
我去找朋友來，別急
I’ll go get a guy I know.
Hang loose.
他來了
相機拿去
-Here he is.
-Take the camera.
小子，如何？
Well, kid?
你不是攝影師嗎？讓相機動，我們不會弄
Aren’t you a photographer?
Make the camerawork. We can’t do it.
幫我們照相
Take our picture.
-你弄壞了 -不是我
-It wasn’t me.
-You fucking broke it.
要轉一下
I found it.
It has to be wound.
-你叫什麼？ -阿炮
-What’s your name?
-Rocket.
阿炮，再來一張
-Another picture, Rocket.
-How about two rows?
-排成兩排好了 -什麼？
排成兩排，把槍拿著
-What?
-Two rows. Everyone with their guns.
-喂，你出鏡了
-口氣好一點
-You’re outside, for Christ’s sake!
-Talk to him nicely, kid.
抱歉，請站進來
Sorry. Move in, please.
再一張
Another one.
-底片沒了
-那就拿出來看
-I think the roll’s finished.
-Then show us the pictures.
得拿去洗
-They have to be developed.
-Developed?
洗？要多少錢？
How much is it?
這些錢拿去，洗好拿給我
我拿底片
Take this money.
And bring back the pictures.
不必，整台拿去
-I have to remove the film.
-Keep the camera.
班尼不是要送你？拿去吧
didn’t he? So, it’s yours...
Benny wanted to give it to you,
謝了
Thanks.
別忘了拿照片來
相片，阿炮
Don’t forget the pictures.
The photos, Rocket!
-皮耶 -怎樣？
-Pierre!
-What?
可以幫我洗嗎？
Can you develop this for me?
不行，會惹上麻煩
I can’t, Rocket.
I could get into trouble.
社裡的記者才能在這裡洗
It’s only for the paper’s reporters.
I could risk my job.
皮耶，這些幫我洗
-Pierre?
-Yes, Rogerio?
還有這卷，好嗎？
Develop these for me.
This one too, okay?
我去吃飯了
I’m going to lunch.
你真幸運，要洗多大？
什麼？
You’re lucky. What size?
你要放多大？
-What?
-For the enlargement, what size?
你幫我決定吧
Well... Whatever you think is best.
-拿去 -謝了
-Here.
-Thanks.
我完了
I’m in deep shit now.
死定了
I’m as good as dead.
有人把我送上死路
Someone had signed
my death sentence.
我要揍扁他的臉
I wanted to bash the jerk's face in.
你是瑪莉娜？你偷我的照片
Are you Marina?
Because of you I’m dead.
你害死我了
You stole my photos.
什麼意思？小聲一點
Dead? Stole? What do you mean?
Not so loud.
小聲？你害我會被殺
I’ll be killed because of you.
Not so loud?
你不在，照片擺在那裡
You were gone,
your photos were in the lab.
我也沒辦法
There's nothing I can do.
The photos in our lab...
研究室的照片就是要登的
are photos to be published
in the paper.
我看到就拿來登了
I saw the photos,
I published them.
-你把它偷走 -我沒有，在這裡
-You stole them.
-I did not. Here they are.
-撿起來給我 -等一下…
-Give them to me.
-Just a second.
拿去
Here are your photos.
-還有嗎？
-冷靜一下，你叫什麼？
-Are there any others?
-Calm down. What’s your name?
-阿炮 -阿炮？
-Rocket.
-Rocket?
你好，我是瑪莉娜
I’m Marina.
Nice to meet you.
你別激動 我有照片使用費要給你
Now, relax. I have money for you.
For your pictures.
我們登照片就會付錢給攝影師
Here, when we use a picture
we pay the photographer.
-你想當攝影師？ -對
-Do you want to be a photographer?
-Yes.
-帥喔，上頭版
-你是怎麼照到的？
-Great start! On the front page.
-How’d you get these photos?
我住在那裡
-I live there.
-Rocket...
阿炮，沒有攝影師進得去
no photographer has ever been able
to go in there.
要是你能照更多小霸王的照片
If you could bring us
more pictures of Li’l Z’...
報社會買，我們會付錢
the paper would buy them.
We’d pay you.
你行嗎？
Could you?
我不知道
I don’t know.
問題在哪裡？
What’s the problem?
我晚上不能過去了
The problem? I can’t go there
anymore at night.
-太冒險了
-那白天呢？
-And during the day?
-It’s too risky.
你看，他們終於知道我是老大
Look, man! They’ve finally
understood that I’m the boss.
你朋友叫什麼？
What’s your
photographer-friend’s name?
阿炮
Rocket.
他真行，我要多買幾份去發
He’s good. I’ll take more
to show the others.
怎樣，要不要？
So, Rocket, is it yes or no?
這是個大好機會
It’s a great opportunity.
好吧
Okay.
-我給你底片、鏡頭
-正確的選擇，很好
-You made the right choice. Very good!
-I’ll give you some film, lenses...
乾脆換台相機 我帶你去器材室
and even another camera.
I’ll show you the equipment room.
還有一個問題
There’s another problem.
-什麼？ -我今晚要睡哪裡？
-What is it?
-Where can I sleep tonight?
我不能回去
I can’t go back now.
這是135釐米的
你會在近還是遠？
This is a 135 mm.
Will you be close up or far away?
遠
Far away.
-會調光圈嗎？ -會
-Can you measure the light?
-Yes.
你太近了吧？
Aren’t you too close?
我居然敢找他們理論 也許我會死
I don’t know what spurred me
to go talk to them like that.
Maybe I was going to die...
但現在我有一台相機
but now I had a camera...
有機會當攝影師
and a chance to become
a photographer.
小心狗屎
Watch out for the dog shit.
而且現在才剛入夜
Not to mention that
the night was still young...
想吃東西嗎？
不了
-Want something to eat?
-No thank you, ma'am.
不吃？也不喝？
來根大麻煙？
Nothing to eat? Nothing to drink?
A joint?
試試看
Try this...
該睡覺了
It’s time to go to sleep.
我帶你進房
I’ll show you your bed.
－有，你沒洗過熱水澡？你有熱水吧？
-You have hot water, don’t you?
You’ve never taken a hot shower?
-Yes.
-沒有 -那怎麼辦？
-No.
-What do you do?
我們都用水壺燒
We heat up the kettle.
你幹嘛杵著？
我睡哪一間？
-Why are you standing there?
-What room do I sleep in?
Unfortunately, there’s only one room.
很不幸的只有一間 你得跟我睡
You have to sleep with me.
我就不多談我的初體驗了
I won’t go into the details
of my first sexual experience.
放輕鬆
Just relax...
因為在另一邊
Because, elsewhere...
對貧民區更重要的事正在上演
another more important sex scene
for the ghetto was taking place.
紅毛一槍未開就救走帥奈德
Carrot was helping
Knockout Ned escape...
without firing a shot.
守衛忙著任護士擺佈
The policeman guarding him was
in the willing hands of the nurse.
在此同時，為了除掉紅毛
And in the meantime...
小霸王正斥資買軍火
to eliminate Carrot, Li’l Z'
was investing in munitions.
手筆很大…不過他付不起
even if he couldn’t pay...
He invested heavily,
記得雙管槍嗎？
我已經有了
-Remember the double-barrel?
-I already have it.
This is a repeater rifle. You don’t have
這是自動步槍 你沒有白朗寧
this one, the Browning.
-射飛機都行
-我又不射飛機
-It’ll shoot down a plane.
-I’m not shooting down planes.
，我要的貨呢？AR-15步槍
And the one I asked for?
The AR-15, Uncle Sam.
巴西弄不到
You can’t get them in Brazil.
屁啦
My ass, Uncle Sam.
我有辦法
I have a solution.
看過魯格槍嗎？
The Rugger. Ever seen one?
口徑一樣，只是比較輕
It’s like the AR-15.
Same caliber, but lighter.
有紅外線瞄準？四百連發？
With an infrared sight?
400 shots a minute?
-看情況
-看你個頭，你想耍我？
-It depends.
-It depends, my ass!
Trying to fuck me over?
I’ll fuck you over first.
我先整死你 你給我空手離開
You leave now without the money
or the guns.
-那是你的事
-那我怎麼交待？
-That’s your problem.
-What do I tell the boss?
-你自己想
-你聽到了，出去
-You’ll think of something.
-You heard him, chubby? Get out.
滾啊，肥豬
Beat it, fatso.
小霸王犯了大錯
Li’l Z' had made a big mistake.
售貨員背後都有供應商
He should have known that behind
every salesman lies a supplier.
他們可不好惹
And they don't joke around.
這個你看過嗎？
Have you seen this?
他們要AR-15幹嘛？
What do they need an AR-15 for?
警方會被迫調查
These stories will push
the police to investigate.
你被捉，我也會遭殃
They’ll nab you.
And me, along with you.
我不會招出你
Think I’m going
to give you away?
放心，我會處理
Don’t worry,
I’ll take care of it.
別再搞砸了
But don’t fuck up again.
查理
Charlie!
過來
Come here!
聽著，你告訴他…
Listen...
you tell him...
去找那個混蛋算帳
Let’s go make that sleazy
little dealer pay up.
小子們，過來
Come here, kids!
-喜歡吃雞肉嗎？ -看情形
-Do you like chicken?
-It depends.
我們先吃雞，再拿紅毛當甜點
We’ll eat some chicken
and have Carrot for dessert.
我有禮物要送你們
I have a present for you.
拿去
Here...
這支給你
A big one for you.
真的要送我們？
Are you really giving us
these guns?
對，但你們得幫我對付紅毛
Yes, but I want you on my side,
against Carrot.
然後就可以搶劫？
Then can we hold up
anyone we want?
不能搶貧民區
-會用槍嗎？ -會一點
Not in the ghetto.
Can you shoot?
會一點？
-More or less.
-More or less?
喂，過來教教他們
Hey, you guys, come help
these kids.
我知道，就是這樣
I know. You do it like this.
（結束的開始）
THE BEGINNING OF THE END
捉住那只雞
Get that chicken!
快點
C'mon, let’s go.
小霸王會宰了你
If Li’l Z' catches you,
he'll kill you.
他得先找到我
Yeah, well, he's gotta
find me first.
小子，捉住那只雞
Hey, kid! Get that chicken!
媽的，條子
Shit! The cops!
不准跑
Hell, don't fucking run off!
給我
Give me that.
梅隆海，娘娘腔
Hey, Melonhead! You fucking fag!
給我滾出去
Get the hell out of here!
懦夫
混蛋
Coward!
Asshole!
走吧，讓他們自相殘殺
Come on, let them kill each other.
讓他們去死
They can fuck themselves.
阿炮，幫我們照相
Rocket! Take a picture of us!
你還等什麼？
What are you waiting for?
怎麼回事？
What’s happening?
媽的
Shit!
我們走
Let’s go!
快跑…
Run! Run!
殺了他們，轟了他
Watch out!
Kill one of these faggots!
Blast him!
帥奈德
Knockout Ned!
小心，別動
Take it easy. Don’t move.
好痛
It hurts, man.
別使力
Easy does it, kid.
你為何加入火拼？
Why did you join this fucking war?
帥奈德
小霸王中槍了，快走
Knockout Ned!
Li’l Z’ has been hit. Come on!
等我來救你，撐住
Wait here, I’ll help you.
Just hold on.
-你叫什麼？ -奧圖
-What's your name?
-My name's Otto.
我想幹掉殺父仇人
I want to get my father’s murderer.
Knockout Ned! Li’l Z’ has been hit.
Come on!
等我來救你，撐住
I’ll help you.
Just hold on there.
條子來了
The fucking cops!
趴下
On the ground!
-別動 -手放在頭上
-Hands over your head.
-Don't move!
-我就是要捉你 -你完了，老兄
-You’re the one I want.
-You’re finished, pal.
銬住他
Handcuff him.
你要去哪裡？
Rocket, where are you going?
有件事我想搞清楚
I got something to clear up.
還好嗎？
Okay, lovebirds?
走吧，我們去算帳 你不必，你要給媒體拍
Come on, Li’l Z',
let’s go settle our scores.
Not you. You’re a present
for the media.
有1萬嗎？
Does it come to 10,000?
差不多，我只有這些
Almost. That’s all I have.
只有這些，我們搜過了
-That’s all there was, Chief.
-We searched everywhere.
放了他
Let him go.
這個戒指是金的嗎？
What about this ring?
Is it gold?
把錢裝滿，其他先欠著
Fill it up. You’ll owe us
the rest.
拼什麼拼
Fucking war!
奈德死了，我破產
Knockout Ned is dead
and I'm dead broke!
你玩完了？
You're fucked, eh?
小子們
Kids...
我們得搶幾個錢重振旗鼓
we’ll have to do a few hold-ups
to get my business going again.
-你想重振旗鼓？
-你有意見嗎？
-Your business, Li’l Z’?
-What’s your problem, kid?
這是替我們的朋友報仇
This is for our friend,
motherfucker!
變天囉
A Soviet attack!
該我們當家了
The business is ours!
這張可以讓我拿高薪
This picture of the hood
will get me the job.
這張能讓我成名
This one will make me famous.
甚至登上雜誌封面
It’ll even make the cover
of a magazine.
我不必擔心小霸王了
I won’t have to worry
about Li’l Z' anymore.
但條子呢？
But the cops?
※自封天主之城領袖的流氓§ ※遭人射殺§
GANGSTER, SELF-STYLED "BOSS"
OF THE CITY OF GOD, SHOT DEAD
這張照片會害死我們？
This photo could’ve gotten
us killed?
我覺得會
I think so.
至少你有工作了
At least it got you a job.
不是工作，是實習
總有薪水吧？
-It pays a little, doesn’t it?
-Not a job, an internship.
一點點
A little.
那個女記者夠辣嗎？
What about that lady journalist?
Was she a good lay?
-還好吧 -你不喜歡？
-You didn’t like it?
-More or less.
我覺得記者都很遜
I don't think journalists know how
to screw.
大概吧，可哥亞搶了三戶人家
Yeah, I guess so.
最好宰了他
Cocoa robbed 3 houses in Barra.
誰殺了羅傑？
Better kill him.
Who shot Roger?
-是牛肉 -殺了他
-It was Beef.
-Kill that fucker.
警長和葛林哥也該殺
We should kill the Chief
and Gringo as well.
-我們殺兩個，你們殺三個
-那櫻桃呢？
-Let’s go. Us two, and 3 others...
-What about Cherry?
就這麼決定
It’s a deal.
你們聽過紅衛兵嗎？
Have you heard
of the Red Brigade?
沒有，不過來了照殺
No, but if they come,
we’ll kill them.
-誰會寫字？ -我會一點
-Who knows how to write?
-Me, sort of.
我們列個通殺黑名單
Let’s make a black list.
We’ll kill them all.
把夜鷹放上去
還有酷奇
-Put fucking Nightowl on there.
-And Croquet.
雷諾欠我錢
Leonard, too, he owes me money.
中國佬自以為性感
he thinks he’s hot stuff.
And China-Man,
-巨人呢？
-還有克勞帝歐
-Where’s Giant?
-And Claudio.
巨人，快點
Come on, Giant!
我忘了說，我現在不叫阿炮
I forgot to say,
my name isn't Rocket anymore.
我是攝影師威爾森羅利吉
I’m now Wilson Rodrigues...
BASED ON A REAL STORY
photographer.
一名天主之城的角頭被捕
Manuel Machado,
a.k.a. Knockout Ned...
人稱帥奈德的曼紐馬恰多
was hospitalized after
being wounded by Li’l Z”s gang.
被小霸王的人打傷送進醫院
本台記者專訪到他
On leaving the hospital,
our reporter interviewed him.
死了很多人
大部分是無辜的
Many have died.
Mostly innocent people.
僅僅認識我...
Just knowing me is enough...
僅僅是我的朋友...
just being my friend...
如果他認為誰認識我
他就會殺了他們
If he thinks someone knows me,
he'll kill them.
警方都不管嗎?
The police don’t go in there?
他們捉我，不捉他
They go after me, not him.
我已經進了三次監獄了
然而他卻仍在...
I’ve been in jail 3 times,
while he goes on...
繼續殺人
killing undisturbed.
他們不會拘捕他的
And they don’t arrest him.
帥奈德說火拼將會持續
Knockout Ned says
the war will continue.
蓋德警長保證將逮捕雙方人馬
Police Chief Guedes has promised to
arrest both gangs in the City of God.